And since you think your job is interesting,
وبما أنك تشعر بأن عملك ممتع ستقول "أنا مختص بالرياضيات"
And inevitably, during that conversation
وخلال هذا الحديث حتما
one of these two phrases come up:
سنحصل على واحدة من إجابتين
A) "I was terrible at math, but it wasn't my fault.
أولا: كنت سيئا في الرياضيات ولم يكن خطأي
It's because the teacher was awful." (Laughter)
لأن المدرس كان سيئا
Or B) "But what is math really for?"
أو ثانيا: وما هو الغرض من الرياضيات
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I'll now address Case B.
أما الحالة الثانية فنناقشها الآن
When someone asks you what math is for, they're not asking you
عندما يسألك شخص ما عن ما هو نفع الرياضيات
about applications of mathematical science.
فهم لا يسالونك حول تطبيقات علوم الرياضيات
They're asking you,
بل يسالونك ، لماذا ندرس هذا الهراء
why did I have to study that bullshit I never used in my life again? (Laughter)
الذي لن نستخدمه مجددا في حياتنا
That's what they're actually asking.
هذا هو سؤالهم الحقيقي
So when mathematicians are asked what math is for,
لذلك عندما تسال الرياضيين لماذا الرياضيات
they tend to fall into two groups:
سيكونون على شكل مجموعتين
54.51 percent of mathematicians will assume an attacking position,
سيأخذ 54،51% من الرياضيين موقفا هجوميا
and 44.77 percent of mathematicians will take a defensive position.
بينما يأخذ 44،77% موقفا دفاعيا
There's a strange 0.8 percent, among which I include myself.
وهناك 0،8% وأنا منهم سيهجمون
Who are the ones that attack?
من هم الذين سيهجمون؟
The attacking ones are mathematicians who would tell you
المهاجمون هم الرياضيون الذين سيخبرونك
this question makes no sense,
بأن هذا السؤال لا معنى له
because mathematics have a meaning all their own --
لأن الرياضيات لها معناها الخاص
a beautiful edifice with its own logic --
إنها بناء خاص له منطقه الخاص
and that there's no point
وإنه لا معنى
in constantly searching for all possible applications.
في البحث المستمر عن كل التطبيقات الممكنة
What's the use of poetry? What's the use of love?
ما هي فائدة الشعر؟ وما هي فائدة الحب؟
What's the use of life itself? What kind of question is that?
ما فائدة الحياة نفسها؟ أي سؤال هذا ؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Hardy, for instance, was a model of this type of attack.
كان هاردي نموذجا لهذا النوع من الهجوم
And those who stand in defense tell you,
وهؤلاء الذين يقفون للدفاع يخبرونكم
"Even if you don't realize it, friend, math is behind everything."
حتى لو لم تعرف ذلك فالرياضيات وراء كل شيء
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Those guys,
هؤلاء الرجال
they always bring up bridges and computers.
الذين يتكلمون عن الجسور و الحاسبات
"If you don't know math, your bridge will collapse."
"إذا لا تفهم الرياضيات سينهار الجسر"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's true, computers are all about math.
نعم صحيح الحاسبات كلها عن الرياضيات
And now these guys have also started saying
وهؤلاء الرجال بدأوا بالقول
that behind information security and credit cards are prime numbers.
بأن وراء أمن المعلومات وبطاقات الأئتمان
These are the answers your math teacher would give you if you asked him.
هناك أعداد أولية هذا هو جواب المدرس
He's one of the defensive ones.
الرياضيات وهذا أحد الأجوبة الدفاعية
Okay, but who's right then?
جيد .. ولكن ما هو الصحيح إذا ؟
Those who say that math doesn't need to have a purpose,
أولئك القائلين بأن ليس للرياضيات سبب
or those who say that math is behind everything we do?
أو أولئك الذين يقولون بأنها وراء كل شيء
Actually, both are right.
ولكن في الحقيقة فالأثنين على صواب
But remember I told you
ولكن تذكروا ما قلت لكم
I belong to that strange 0.8 percent claiming something else?
أنا من 0،8% الذين يدعون شيئا آخر
So, go ahead, ask me what math is for.
هيا إسألوني ما الغرض من الرياضيات
Audience: What is math for?
المتفرجون: لماذا الرياضيات ؟
Eduardo Sáenz de Cabezón: Okay, 76.34 percent of you asked the question,
جيد 76،34% منكم سأل السؤال
23.41 percent didn't say anything,
و 23،41% لم يتكلموا
and the 0.8 percent --
والباقون 0،8% ...
I'm not sure what those guys are doing.
لا أدري ماذا يفعل هؤلاء
Well, to my dear 76.31 percent --
وأقول لأعزائي 76،31%
it's true that math doesn't need to serve a purpose,
نعم لا تحتاج الرياضيات الحقيقية لخدمة سبب
it's true that it's a beautiful structure, a logical one,
نعم هي في الحقيقة هيكل جميل و منطقي
probably one of the greatest collective efforts
ويمكن أن تكون من أعظم الجهود الجماعية
ever achieved in human history.
التي توصلنا لها في تاريخ البشرية
But it's also true that there,
ولكن من الصحيح أيضا بأن هناك
where scientists and technicians are looking for mathematical theories
علماء و رياضيين يبحثون عن نظريات رياضية
that allow them to advance,
التي تسمح لهم بالتقدم
they're within the structure of math, which permeates everything.
وهم داخل هيكل الرياضيات التي تغطي كل شيء
It's true that we have to go somewhat deeper,
نعم علينا فعلا الدخول أعمق
to see what's behind science.
لنرى ماذا وراء العلم
Science operates on intuition, creativity.
العلم يعمل بالحدس والأبداع
Math controls intuition and tames creativity.
الرياضيات تسيطر على الحدس و ترعى الابداع
Almost everyone who hasn't heard this before
ومن لم يسمع هذا سابقا
is surprised when they hear that if you take
سيتعجبون عندما يسمعون بأنك لو أخذت
a 0.1 millimeter thick sheet of paper, the size we normally use,
ورقة عادية بسمك 0.1 ملم من الحجم الذي نستخدمه يوميا
and, if it were big enough, fold it 50 times,
وإذا كانت كبيرة بما يكفي لطيها 50 مرة
its thickness would extend almost the distance from the Earth to the sun.
سيغطي تقريبا المسافة بين الارض والشمس
Your intuition tells you it's impossible.
حدسك سيقول بأن ذلك مستحيل
Do the math and you'll see it's right.
إحسبها بالرياضيات وستجد ذلك صحيحا
That's what math is for.
هذا هو سبب وجود الرياضيات
It's true that science, all types of science, only makes sense
صحيح إن العلوم كلها تكون معقولة
because it makes us better understand this beautiful world we live in.
فهي تزيد فهمنا لعالمنا الجميل حيث نعيش
And in doing that,
وبذلك فهي تساعدنا
it helps us avoid the pitfalls of this painful world we live in.
على تجنب المطبات في هذا العالم المؤلم
There are sciences that help us in this way quite directly.
هناك علوم تساعدنا مباشرة في هذا السبيل
Oncological science, for example.
مثلا طب السرطان
And there are others we look at from afar, with envy sometimes,
وهناك علوم أخرى ننظر لها من بعد بغيرة
but knowing that we are what supports them.
ولكننا نعرف اننا ندعمها
All the basic sciences support them,
وجميع العلوم الأخرى تدعمها
including math.
وضمنها الرياضيات
All that makes science, science is the rigor of math.
كل هذا يصنع العلوم وهي أساس الرياضيات
And that rigor factors in because its results are eternal.
وهذه الأسس تصنع عوامل نتائجها خالدة
You probably said or were told at some point
لا بد إنكم قلتم أو سمعتم يوما ما
that diamonds are forever, right?
بأن الماس خالد أليس كذلك؟
That depends on your definition of forever!
وهذا يعتمد على تعريفكم للخلود
A theorem -- that really is forever.
نظريا هذا يعني إلى ما لا نهاية
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The Pythagorean theorem is still true
نظرية فيثاغورس لا تزال صحيحة
even though Pythagoras is dead, I assure you it's true. (Laughter)
رغم إن فيثاغورس مات أؤكد لكم إنها صحيحة
Even if the world collapsed
حتى لو إنهار العالم
the Pythagorean theorem would still be true.
ستبقى نظرية فيثاغورس صحيحة
Wherever any two triangle sides and a good hypotenuse get together
عندما يتصل ضلعي مثلث قائمان ووتر ..
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
the Pythagorean theorem goes all out. It works like crazy.
وتعمل نظرية قيثاغورس دائما وتعمل بجنون
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Well, we mathematicians devote ourselves to come up with theorems.
وقد نذرالرياضيون أنفسهم لأيجاد ووضع نظريات
Eternal truths.
الحقائق الخالدة
But it isn't always easy to know the difference between
ولكن ليس من السهل دائما معرفة الفرق بين
an eternal truth, or theorem, and a mere conjecture.
حقيقة خالدة و حدس عادي
You need proof.
أنت تحتاج إلى الأثبات
For example,
مثلا
let's say I have a big, enormous, infinite field.
لنفرض إن لدي حقلا كبيرا جدا لا متناهيا
I want to cover it with equal pieces, without leaving any gaps.
وأريد أن أغطيه بقطع متساوية بدون ترك فراغ
I could use squares, right?
أستطيع إستخدام المربعات .. صحيح؟
I could use triangles. Not circles, those leave little gaps.
أو مثلثات ولكن ليس دوائرفهي تترك فراغات
Which is the best shape to use?
أي شكل هو الأحسن للأستخدام؟
One that covers the same surface, but has a smaller border.
الشكل الذي له نفس المساحة بأصغر محيط
In the year 300, Pappus of Alexandria said the best is to use hexagons,
قال بابوس من الأسكندرية عام 300 إن الأحسن
just like bees do.
هو إستخدام الشكل السداسي كما يعمل النحل
But he didn't prove it.
لكنه لم يثبت كلامه
The guy said, "Hexagons, great! Let's go with hexagons!"
قال إن الشكل السداسي جيد فلنستخدمه
He didn't prove it, it remained a conjecture.
لم يثبته وبقي ذلك حدسا
"Hexagons!"
"الشكل السداسي"
And the world, as you know, split into Pappists and anti-Pappists,
وإنقسم الناس بين مؤيدين و معارضين
until 1700 years later
و مرت 1700 سنة بعد ذلك
when in 1999, Thomas Hales proved
عندما قام توماس هيلز عام 1999 بإثبات
that Pappus and the bees were right -- the best shape to use was the hexagon.
أن المؤيدين والنحل على حق وإن الأفضل هو
And that became a theorem, the honeycomb theorem,
الشكل السداسي.أصبحت لدينا نظرية خلية النحل
that will be true forever and ever,
والتي ستكون صحيحة إلى الأبد
for longer than any diamond you may have. (Laughter)
أكثر من أي ماسة لديكم (ضحك)
But what happens if we go to three dimensions?
ولكن ماذا لو ذهبنا إلى الابعاد الثلاثة ؟
If I want to fill the space with equal pieces,
إذا أردت أن أملأ الفضاء بقطع متساوية
without leaving any gaps,
بدون أن نترك أي فراغات بينها
I can use cubes, right?
يمكنني استخدام المكعبات، صحيح ؟
Not spheres, those leave little gaps. (Laughter)
ليس الكرات لأنها تترك فراغات
What is the best shape to use?
ما هو الشكل الأفضل للأستخدام ؟
Lord Kelvin, of the famous Kelvin degrees and all,
قال اللورد كيلفن المشهور بدرجة حرارة كيلفن وغيرها
said that the best was to use a truncated octahedron
بأن أحسن الأشكال هو المثمن المجسم المقطوع
which, as you all know --
وكما تعرفون جميعا إنه ..
(Laughter) --
(ضحك)
is this thing here!
هذا الجسم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Come on.
رجاءا
Who doesn't have a truncated octahedron at home? (Laughter)
من ليس لديه مثمن مجسم مقطوع في بيته؟ (ضحك)
Even a plastic one.
حتى لو كان بلاستيكيا
"Honey, get the truncated octahedron, we're having guests."
عزيزتي هاتي مثمن مجسم مقطوع لدينا ضيوف
Everybody has one! (Laughter)
كل شخص لديه واحد (ضحك)
But Kelvin didn't prove it.
ولكن كلفن لم يثبت ذلك وبقي الموضوع حدسا
It remained a conjecture -- Kelvin's conjecture.
حدسا من قبل كلفن
The world, as you know, then split into Kelvinists and anti-Kelvinists
وإنقسم العالم كالعادة مع و ضد كلفن
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
until a hundred or so years later,
وبعد مرور مائة سنة تقريبا بعد ذلك
someone found a better structure.
وجد أحدهم هيكلا افضل
Weaire and Phelan found this little thing over here --
وجد ويير و فيلان هذا الشيء الصغير
(Laughter) --
(ضحك)
this structure to which they gave the very clever name
هذا الهيكل الذي أعطياه إسما ذكيا
"the Weaire-Phelan structure."
مجسم ويير و فيلان
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It looks like a strange object, but it isn't so strange,
فهو يبدو مثل جسم غريب لكنه ليس غريبا تماما
it also exists in nature.
وهو موجود في الطبيعة أيضا
It's very interesting that this structure,
ومن الممتع إن هذا الهيكل
because of its geometric properties,
وبسبب خواصه الهندسية
was used to build the Aquatics Center for the Beijing Olympic Games.
أستخدم لبناء المركز المائي في بكين لأولمبياد بكين
There, Michael Phelps won eight gold medals,
حيث حصل مايكل فلبس على ست مداليات ذهبية
and became the best swimmer of all time.
وأصبح أحسن سباح في التاريخ
Well, until someone better comes along, right?
إنه الأفضل لحين ظهور شيء أفضل
As may happen with the Weaire-Phelan structure.
كما قد يحصل لمجسم ويير فيلان
It's the best until something better shows up.
إنه الأفضل حتى يظهر شيء أحسن منه
But be careful, because this one really stands a chance
ولنكن حذرين لأن هذا الأحتمال وارد
that in a hundred or so years, or even if it's in 1700 years,
بأنه خلال 100 سنة أو حتى 1700 سنة
that someone proves it's the best possible shape for the job.
سيثبت شخص ما مجسما أفضل لهذا العمل
It will then become a theorem, a truth, forever and ever.
فتصبح عند ذاك نظرية أو حقيقة تدوم ابدا
For longer than any diamond.
أطول من أي ماسة
So, if you want to tell someone
فإذا أردت أن تقول لأحد
that you will love them forever
بأنك ستحبه دائما
you can give them a diamond.
فقدم له ماسة
But if you want to tell them that you'll love them forever and ever,
ولكن إذا أردت القول بأنك تحبه إلى الأبد
give them a theorem!
فأعطه نظرية
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But hang on a minute!
ولكن توقف لدقيقة
You'll have to prove it,
عليك أن تثبتها
so your love doesn't remain
وبذلك لا يبقى حبك
a conjecture.
حدسا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)